Kelly Costello. Now, just let us, we'll carefully introduce ourselves.
In the room here we have the officials from MB,
and they will be listening to this, and then we'll be speaking to them afterwards.
I'm Greg O'Connor. I'm the chair of the Select Committee.
I'm seated at the center of the table.
On my left is-
Kia ora. I'm Cindy Wade-Brown. Nice to see you on the Zoom
And on my right-
Kia ora koutou. I'm Brett Young, Member of Parliament for Maungakiekie
And I'm Andrew Bayly, Auckland Central member
All right. Now, Ms. Kelly Costello, do you mind if I-- Aine is it?
Aine, yep.
Aine. If you don't mind if, Aine. If you're happy with me calling Aine?
Yeah
And if you're happy. So we've got your submission, and we've read it.
If you've got 10 minutes to use how you will, feel free to speak to it.
But it would be useful if you left some time for questions at the end for the
members. So,
introduce yourself.
Thank you. We were indicated that we had 15 minutes in total.
Is that still the case?
Yes.
Oh, my apologies. You do have 15 minutes, yes.
There we go. There we go.
Thank you. So yeah, we will do that.
So here with me is Nithin Mankil and Frans Merrits.
But tena koutou, thank you all for your time today and for introducing yourselves.
So my name is Aine, and Nithin and Frans are here from Migrants
Against the Acceptable Standard of Health Aotearoa, MASHAA.
And as immigrants to Aotearoa, we've seen the beautiful and welcoming side of this
country, but we also continue to feel the impact of a policy that has the opposite
effect by deeming many migrants with disabilities and health conditions cost
burdens to the state.
MASHAA does two linked things. We systemically advocate to abolish the acceptable
standard of health requirements, and we support those impacted now.
So now I'd like to hand to Nithin and then to Frans, who will both share what
impact the ASSH requirements have had on them and on their families' lives.
So over to you, Nithin.
Well, welcome, gentlemen.
Thank you for the time.
My name is Nithin Mankil, and I am the father of Aiden Nithin, a six-year-old boy.
I'm writing on behalf of my family.
My wife and I are both holders of New Zealand residence visa.
We are originally from Kerala, India and are currently living in Nelson.
We both are health professional, myself registered nurse, and my wife is a
healthcare assistant. We initially submitted a family residence visa application
that include our son, Aiden, who was on general visitor visa at that time.
During the medical examination in New Zealand, Aiden was diagnosed with autism
spectrum disorder. Following this, immigration officer advised us over the phone to
remove Aiden from the residency application and proceed without him, to apply for a
different visa category for
him separately, as he didn't meet the acceptable standard of health requirement.
Based on that advice, we continue our application, and my wife and I granted a
residency visa in June 2025. As Aiden's visitor visa was nearly expired,
I submitted a new visa application.
Unfortunately, this application was declined, as a result, Aiden become unlawful.
We then appealed for Honorable Associate Minister Immigration, Chris Penk, on
fourth August 2025. On November 2025, we received
a response stating that the minister can't able to intervene in this matter.
This situation was extremely distressing and heartbreaking for our family.
The thought of being separated from our only child is emotionally overwhelming.
We are mentally exhausted, often in tears all the days, and struggling to find a
solution. We are living in a constant fear of family separation because he's the
only one we have. We cannot send him back, as there is no one there who can
properly care of him. We have worked hard since our college years to build a life
in New Zealand and contribute to this beautiful country.
Then we have started a petition to seek support and are continuing our effort to
fight for our son.
Aiden is a joyful and deeply loved child who has a strong interest in music,
swinging, and all the outdoor activities.
He's generally a calm boy, but unfortunately, he's diagnosed with autism spectrum
disorder. And the decision to deport and reject his visa is deeply
distressing and feel unjust. It's profoundly concerning that in this day and age, a
child is not being fully considered due to his disability.
Such action can seem a lack of compassion and do not reflect the value of an
inclusive and human society.
Our son, Aiden, has potential to achieve many things if he get the support from his
parents and the society. So this all about my story.
Thank you so much.
Well, thank you.
Yeah. And over to you now, Frans.
Hey, good day, everyone. Thanks for the time.
Yeah, Chair, members of the committee,
yeah, thank you for the few minutes that we can share our story here.
My name is Frans Merrits, and I'm here for my son, my family, and every migrant
family affected by the acceptable standard of health.
Our story is quite personal.
And sorry if my voice is going to get croaky because it's been a very long battle.
But this problem is much bigger than just us.
So for almost 10 years,
the immigration system kept our son away from our family because he did not meet
the ASSH policy. My son suffered a stroke at birth, which was nothing
to do, you know, his fault. He has a speech and development delay,
but has improved significantly as a human being.
But that doesn't define him. He is my son, he is a brother to my boys, and he's a
human being.
And we lost almost 10 years together because a policy calculated what he might cost
New Zealand.
10 years. That's 10 birthdays, 10 Christmases, brothers growing apart, moments
we'll never get back.
So I ask you, with tears in my eyes, you know, what's 10 years worth of a child's
life?
ASSH calculates the potential cost of my son, but who calculates the cost of ASSH
on our family?
We are paying it now. We're picking up pieces of a family damaged by years of
separation.
And we will have to carry that life sentence for a very long time.
Throughout this journey, particularly on social media, we have heard, you know, "If
you don't like it here, go back to your own country."
Mm.
But the Kiwi who actually knows us have said something very different.
They said, "Frans, this is wrong. I am ashamed this is happening in New Zealand."
Surely that tells us something.
When ordinary New Zealanders look at policy and say, "This is not how Kiwis
represent the world", shouldn't we listen?
And to those who tell us to go back, I'm saying a hard no.
This is my country as well.
Mm.
We stayed because we love New Zealand. We fought because we believe in it.
And even while our family was hurting, we kept giving back to our community.
I personally have built businesses here,
and I've coached junior rugby for years.
Here in my local area in Beachlands,
I volunteered as a club president. I've fundraised a lot.
Mm.
And I'm doing it because I love the sport.
I love to see how the sport changes young men or young boys into incredible
men.
And coaching isn't just about rugby, it's about the discipline, the respect, the
resilience,
and about helping boys become, like I said, better men
So what is that contribution worth?
What if I had arrived here with a heart condition?
Would
that have made me worth less?
Could a medical assessment have predicted my contribution to my community? No.
And if you couldn't calculate my potential, how can you calculate my son's
potential? Human potential cannot be measured on a spreadsheet.
I understand our health system and education systems are under pressure,
but has ESS become the easy answer to a difficult problem?
If healthcare is struggling, we need to fix it, and if education is struggling with
resources, we need to fix that too.
Do not make children pay for problems they did not create.
New Zealand has committed itself to the right and dignity of disabled people, yet
the United Nations has already raised concerns about discrimination resulting from
this ESS policy. What are those commitments worth if we hide behind policy when
these become difficult or expensive?
Our family has already paid the price. You cannot give us those 10 years back.
But you can stop another family from losing theirs.
I am not here for sympathy. I'm not asking for special treatment.
I'm asking for change. Our experience cannot be undone.
But let it mean something. Let it become the reason another child doesn't lose 10
years with their family.
We love New Zealand dearly. We love it enough to believe we can do better.
And you are the lawmakers. You have the power to change this.
ESS is unjust, it's outdated, and it's broken.
I'm not asking for it to be adjusted.
I'm not to be moving the threshold. But we're asking you to abolish it completely.
And let's build a better New Zealand together the way it should be.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you, all of you. It's very emotional and very difficult, so I
appreciate your contribution here today.
Now, the committee have some questions. Greg Fleming.
Yeah. Hey, thank you guys very much for sharing the stories as vulnerably as you
did. Just want to clarify, so you're asking for there to be no standard of
health applied. Is that right?
Anya speaking. Yeah, that is what we're asking.
And the reason for that is that the logic that says that
disabled people, people with health conditions are a cost burden, that's a
harmful logic to apply to anyone. So whether that's to
a child, disabled child, as you've heard, or an adult with a disability or a health
condition or high BMI gets caught in this policy as well.
So we say that we want to start from a strength-based position, a position that
values human beings and their potential and their contributions that they will
bring, and that they will also bring better as family units when you keep a family
together and put in place the conditions where they can all thrive and
give back to their fullest potential.
Yeah, no, I appreciate that. Do you think that genuinely it is an anthropological
question, though? Do you think it's one of the policy is just a result of us
living, unfortunately, in a resource-constrained world?
So the policy
is a political choice. In Canada, the similar policy, their medical
inadmissibility was reviewed back in 2017.
There's a reference for that in the written submission.
And it was lessened considerably, with a path to potentially
removing it entirely over time. And that was specifically on
noting that the values that underpin that policy didn't align with kind of
modern Canadian values of compassion and inclusiveness and things like that.
So, with the political will, this policy can be changed.
Yes, we need to resource health and education systems better, but there are other
ways to raise revenue to do that that don't essentially involve scapegoating our
migrants.
Okay. Thank you.
Oh, Sulia White-Brown.
Thank you. Anya and colleagues, you brought some very moving stories to us.
And in fact, you started, Anya, on what I want to know more about, which is the
Canadian system. And have you-- And if you haven't, don't worry, we
can ask for information. Have you heard about any positive or negative
results after they lowered the bar?
I mean, the bar at the moment seems to me to be a breach of human rights, but we
have some problems with challenging that at the moment.
Well, there's one family who tried for years and years to be able to get their
autistic daughter over here. And then the father, who'd been living here
because they were a split family, ended up getting a job in Canada.
And because they'd removed the education criteria from Canada's, they went to
Canada, and they had no problem, and they got in.
And my heart just kind of broke for them. But there are examples like that.
And so, yeah, many of the families impacted at the moment, it is under
education criteria.
I think it could be worthwhile talking to Canadian officials.
I'm sure you guys have the means to do that.
And yeah, there are a couple of sources there in the written submission as well.
Thank you.
All right. Thanks. Any other questions, members?
Oh, sorry, can I ask one clarifying question?
So Frans-
That's Greg Fleming.
Yeah, sorry. So Frans, where has your son been for these last 10 years?
Sorry, I'm spying on my new button. He's with my parents in South Africa.
So yeah, I don't want to make a long thing about it, but yeah, it's a decision we
made to come over here. We thought it was going to be a quick thing.
We've been fighting the battle ever since.
But we've committed ourselves to New Zealand.
We've been in so deep that there's no-- For us to turn around now and go back would
be everything would be a waste. We'll rather just keep fighting.
I still have hope for New Zealand, and who knows, maybe this was my destiny for my
life to come to New Zealand and do this. I don't know.
But I try and-
So just so I'm clear, you made the decision, though, to move to South Africa
knowing that there was a chance that your son wouldn't be able to come?
Well-
New Zealand.
Yeah.
So we came over, we applied. All our family's got given visas.
So in my opinion, New Zealand gave us hope, like: Look,
one son, we'll keep fighting for him.
We then kept applying. I think you can look at our immigration records, but I think
we've applied five or six times to get through where we are.
And we've went through each and every hoop.
And yeah, we're not getting any closer.
But then you hear of other people that's here with...
So the policy is also there's some double standard somewhere because there are
people coming in here. They are here with the same policies, the same criterias,
and they're in wheelchairs. They are in-- They're also sick.
Why does it go the one way, not the other way?
So if we do have this policy, how can some people get in, others
not? So isn't it just better to abolish it and then work on something that's
actually working for the benefit and for everyone?
And I'll just add on there as well that the Education and Workforce Select
Committee has looked at a couple of ESS petitions before, and they recommended both
times that a strengths-based approach
be taken to this. And so we support that
direction, along with, as Frans said earlier, the fact that the UN Committee
on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities has said that this actually needs to be
reviewed and amended, working closely with disabled people, migrants and refugees
organizations.
All right. Look, thank you very much.
And we've got officials here from MB, and we're going to hear from them now.
So thank you for your very personal stories. I know it's not easy.
So- Um, we appreciate you taking the time today to do that.
Thank you.
So you're very welcome to remain on while we hear from the officials.
Welcome.
Thank you. Would you like us to introduce ourselves first?
Yes, introduce yourselves, and then we've 10 minutes, and we'll-
Yeah.
Um.
Hi, everyone. My name is Polly Vowles.
I manage the Skills and Residence Immigration Policy Team, and we are responsible
for providing advice to the Minister on all the main work and residence visa
settings, including settings around families and the acceptable standard of health.
Thank you.
Uh, kia ora, my name's John Kilroy.
I'm the Deputy Chief Operating Officer at Immigration New Zealand, associated with
visa operations.
Right.
Good afternoon. I'm Fraser Richards.
I'm Special Counsel for Immigration, so from the legal team that supports these
guys.
All right.
Yes.
Welcome.
Thank you. I do want to start by acknowledging the stories we've heard,
very personal stories, and to say that we are really aware that the acceptable
standard of health settings can have a significant impact on migrants and their
families. We see it, and we really acknowledge the difficult trade-offs that this
policy is trying to manage.
Fundamentally, the Immigration Act requires the immigration system to balance the
national interest with individual rights.
It must facilitate migration while reducing risks to public health and minimizing
significant cost and demand on New Zealand's health and living support services.
With the medical waiver provisions providing the flexibility to consider individual
circumstances where appropriate.
These acceptable standard of health settings have operated for more than 20 years
under successive governments and provide a consistent way to assess health-related
risks. They are also able to be updated to remain fit for purpose, such as the
increase in the significant cost threshold in 2022 and the recent removal of
several health conditions where changes to treatment mean that they no longer meet
that threshold. Currently, MBIE considers that the ASSH framework continues to
provide an appropriate balance between these different objectives.
All right. Thank you. Mr. Bailey.
So, the one question mentioned by Frank is the apparent
inconsistency of approach. So he talked to use the example of wheelchair.
Can you just maybe assure us or provide us with guidance around whether in fact
there is an inconsistency or whether that's just a perception?
Sorry, the inconsistency-
He talked about the example of some people in wheelchairs who seem to get through
and then get accepted even though they appear to not meet the health requirements.
So that was the-
Yeah
... allegation, if I can use that word.
Yeah.
I don't know if you meant it like that way, but that was the claim.
Well, I think, the acceptable standard of health is a framework in a way that the
medical system will do, but it also has this ability, these medical waiver
provisions, to consider a wider range of factors, and that can consider economic
factors, humanitarian, family factors.
So not every decision is going to be the same, but I can defer to my legal-
Okay
... and operational colleagues who are closer to these decisions.
And it's hard to know how these perceived inconsistencies come up.
One thing I can point to is when people within the system actually have to provide
medical information to us, which is the most likely time that it will bring forward
issues that might hit the acceptable standard of health.
So generally, although the standard applies across the board, if you're applying
for residence, there is a standard that you have to meet, and you have to provide
full medicals or limited medicals if you have relationships with New Zealanders.
It's only if you're going to be staying in the country for a certain period of time
on a temporary visa that you actually have to submit medicals for the family
members. So inconsistencies may arise depending on the visa that a person has
applied for, whether they've had to submit a medical with their application, or if
they've arrived using ETAs or visa waiver, you may see some of this pop up.
So secondly on that.
This says the child had asphyxia. It was asphyxia, right?
There's obviously different graduations of that.
Could be severe, or it could be very mild, of course.
How do you take that into account in the health assessment?
Because the policy, and I understand why we need a framework for the policy.
I'm not getting at that. But there's a graduation in there.
So can you perhaps just explain how you deal with those graduations?
So when an application for, say, residence is made, there'll be a medical that's
submitted with the application. If there's an indication that there are
ASSH issues, that will get referred to our medical assessors.
So we have a panel of medical assessors that are doctors who will look at the
medical, and then they will let us know whether they think the individual is ASSH
or not ASSH, and then we'll take the process from there.
So in the case of, I don't know how asphyxia works, but say there's a spectrum.
The doctor will look at that and determine whether, based on the information they
see, whether the person's ASSH or not.
So there are medical professionals involved.
Sir, you won't be out.
Thank you. Well, as an immigrant myself, I feel this quite closely.
That if circumstances had been different, I might not have been let in.
And I just wonder
if you have looked at other jurisdictions around the world, particularly
Canada, and seen
whether there's been a huge increase in cost.
Any migrant's children could have an accident after they come here and be quite
expensive. So, all potential risks are still there.
And I just think this policy that seems to separate families is quite
inhumane.
So yes, we have looked at comparable countries, both when we developed the
original, the ASSH framework back in 2003, '04, and over time.
So we do have some anecdotal information from Canadian officials that
the change to significantly reduce the threshold has placed a strain on schools and
public education infrastructure and resources, with higher volumes of children with
complex needs, and that there are increasing bottlenecks in diagnostic and clinical
services causing delays in diagnosis and treatment.
So this is in the context of limited resources and funding.
So I stress that's anecdotal. I can't quantify it.
But that is some information we've received from Canadian officials.
Mr. Williams.
Yeah, thank you. So I appreciate that.
And that's what I was trying to get at in my question as well.
Not for one moment do I think this is a question around New Zealand's view of the
human as the person. It's just around the reality that we live in a
resource-constrained world.
And we have a health and education system that are already burdened.
So my question is, is there any ability at the moment, how with the parent
visa at the moment that's been recently opened up to the point where if they take
medical insurance, so as to head off the possibility of that becoming a burden on
the New Zealand health system. Is that the pathway that's available in these kinds
of circumstances?
Ms. Vowles.
Yeah. We have given consideration to that.
The issue is when someone gains residence, they gain access to publicly funded
services.
Yes, okay.
And we can't guarantee that they'll be able to maintain their insurance over an
incredibly long period of time. People's circumstances change. They lose jobs.
Things, accidents happen, all that kind of stuff.
So that's not something at the moment that we can take into account, their ability
to fund it, because they inherently become entitled to those things.
The thing I would add there is with the parent boost visa, they're actually
required to be ASSH and have insurance as well.
And insurance.
So that's-
So they're-
... an extra requirement.
Yes. Because New Zealand is sufficiently compassionate that if the insurance lapsed
or something, we wouldn't refuse them entry to our hospital.
No, we would not.
Yeah. Okay. Thank you.
All right.
I just think, I should probably, this might not be the right place for me.
Given that ACC covers so many overseas visitors for so many accidents and costs
us so much money-
But it's such a short-term
... and this is so different. No?
What about ACC?
It's probably not fair for-
No, but I feel strongly- ... so-
Initial different.
And I have to correlate that as a parent of a very disabled child.
Yeah.
I do understand that that has probably placed limitations on my ability to live
elsewhere in the world.
Oh.
So that's, I've got to correlate that as well
But look, thank you. You clarified that.
Obviously, for those, I know our submitters will be still listening.
The committee will tie consider where to from here,
recommendations made. So thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
All
right.
Thank you.
And thanks for your work, public servants.
Yeah. Thanks.
Thomas, appreciate it.
All the best.
And thank you, Graham, for your work in the election.
Thank you.
Hey, Nate.
Well done.
Nice to see you, man.
Kia ora, Nate, how are you?
Good.
That's an interesting backdrop you've got there.
Half of your committee are sort of-
That's rare
... sitting back in their seat wrong.
Yeah, it's brilliant. Look at that.
In fact, I'm going to invite you, Nate.
Do you know how to use your blurring in the background?
No. I'll have a look if I can see if I can-
If you can. It's probably can't. I'm just thinking in my head.
Yes, I would agree with that as well. Background blur.
Ooh. Is that better?
Right. There you go. Look, you've just a couple out.
You're just-
That's what labor does to its policy, it blurs it.
All right. You've
started a bit of internet nice warfare on the committee here, Nate.
All right, carry on now. We've read your submission.
You've got 10 minutes, but leave us plenty of time for questions, please.
Yeah.
Kia ora koutou. My name's Nate Brewer, and I'm a year 13 student at Kimihia High
School in the Far North. And I'm the petitioner behind the petition calling for
dyslexia screening, testing, diagnostic assessment to be made universally free for
all New Zealanders in Aotearoa. I want to begin by explaining why I brought this
petition forward. I live with dyslexia.
I know firsthand what it is like to sit in a classroom and have to read, write, and
process information, which takes a lot longer and a lot harder than other people in
that same room. For me, this petition is deeply personal.
Because if it wasn't for my mom, I very well could've slipped through the cracks in
the education system. My mom is a primary school teacher, and because of her
experience, she noticed the way I was reading and writing, and processing
information was different. She recognized that there was something more going on
than simply struggling at school.
She pushed for a dyslexia assessment, and that assessment identified that I had
dyslexia. But I often think about what happens if my mom was not a teacher.
What if parents had not had the knowledge that my mom had?
What if they simply thought I was struggling with reading and writing, and I would
eventually catch up?
I think about the families across New Zealand who are in this exact same position
because not every parent is a teacher.
Not every parent knows that their child may be different, and they
may need special conditions and special learning things.
This means that there could be many students across Aotearoa who are slipping
through the cracks at this very moment because no one around them recognize what is
happening and what their brain is thinking.
And this is why early identification of dyslexia matters so much.
Because dyslexia does not determine how intelligent I am.
It does not determine how hard I work.
But it does determine how much
I struggle in school, and how much school becomes a burden for me.
For me, this petition is fundamentally about fairness.
It is whether or not
access to understanding of how you learn should depend on your parents' income,
where you live, or whether your parents can afford hundreds or even thousands of
dollars for a dyslexia diagnostic assessment.
The Ministry of Education has told this committee that dyslexia assessments in New
Zealand are not typically publicly funded, and families often have to pay
privately. Their own submission states that assessments commonly cost between $700
and $1,500. For most families in New Zealand, this may be manageable, but for a lot
of families, this is an enormous amount of money, and it will really have a
negative effect, and will mean that they actually can't access this.
This creates a problem of equity. If two students with the same learning
difficulties like dyslexia and dyslexia, but one of the students can afford an
assessment and the others can't, we should ask ourselves whether or not we are
comfortable with that difference and opportunities that can follow.
And I would encourage, and I would think that everyone on this committee would
agree otherwise. The Ministry has also made the point that it is,
in its response, it says that students do not need a formal diagnosis to receive
learning support, and that this should be consistent across all schools in New
Zealand. Support should be based on individual learning needs.
But I can tell you from firsthand experience that this is not the case.
Because I have a dyslexia diagnosis, and I sent that to my school, and they came
back and said it is either out of date, and I did it four years ago.
And for me, and for everyone, dyslexia does not disappear in four years.
It is a lifelong specialty that we have.
And I was only given a computer for my exams rather than a reader-writer or using
Dictate, and rather than handwriting my exams.
And for me, there's no difference between typing on a computer and handwriting the
exams. The problem is, is that the thoughts up here, I cannot translate to paper
because of spelling, reading, and just general difficulties around that.
And because there is a difference between,
if the government recognizes that diagnosis can
access and help people have support easier, then
we must ask ourselves, why isn't diagnosis accessible for all families, depending
even though we may have whanau that can't afford it or who are living in poverty.
This is simply not right. The Ministry also points out that work is being
undertaken for identifying dyslexia.
It refers to structured literacy, phonics checks, teacher training, and learning
support coordinators, and other interventions that are designed to identify
students with dyslexia. I support these interventions, but screening in the
classroom and receiving comprehensive diagnosis are not the same.
Teachers can identify when students are struggling. Schools can provide support.
But a proper
qualified specialist can provide a formal assessment that gives students and their
whanau a clear understanding on their learning needs when it comes to dyslexia.
I think we should have both, because early identification is especially important.
Because the Ministry's own submission referred to the 2016 select committee inquiry
that recommended strengthening our identification practices and achieving greater
consistency and support across New Zealand.
10 years later, we are still discussing this problem today, and many rangatahi
across this country are still experiencing not consistent support.
So that should tell us that there's more work to be done.
That brings me to the moral argument behind my petition.
We need to ask ourselves, what kind of education system do we want to have?
Do we want a system where opportunity to understand our own learning depends on our
family's financial position, or do we want a system where every person has a fair
opportunity to understand their learning needs?
For me, this is a question about basic fairness.
If we
believe our education system is a public good, which it is in New Zealand, then
identifying barriers to education should be treated as a public responsibility,
because a child does not choose if they have dyslexia.
A family does not choose to struggle financially, and a student should not have to
choose between paying for an assessment and whanau putting food on the table.
That is wrong. That is why I'm not asking the government to simply spend money
without consideration. I'm asking the government to consider the long-term cost of
not early identification for our rangatahi in our schools.
Because when dyslexia-
Nate, I'll just say, if you wanted to leave time for questions, we're getting near
the end of your submission period.
Okay.
So you're welcome to go for a couple more minutes, but it means there'll be no time
for questions.
Yes, I can jump ahead a little bit. When dyslexia goes unidentified, students can
believe that they are lazy or unintelligent or incapable.
They can lose confidence in our education system.
And they can reach university without fully understanding some aspects of their
learning difficulties
This petition started with my own experience, but it doesn't only include me,
because there are students right now sitting in classrooms who think that they're
not smart enough. There are parents who know that something is wrong, but they
cannot afford an assessment. I believe we can do better, and better can start now.
Because every New Zealander deserves the opportunity to understand how they learn.
Every student deserves a chance to be supported. Thank you for hearing my petition.
Tēnā koutou, tēnā koutou, tēnā koutou katoa.
All right. Thank you, Nate. Do you have a question, Sheila?
Yes. Nate,
thank you very much for your very articulate presentation.
One thing that's very useful is how you've shown that having dyslexia, if
diagnosed, is not a barrier to getting on in the world.
I wondered if you had any friends that had dyslexia diagnosed much
later that have had behavioral problems or other issues that
you think they wouldn't have done if they had a mother like yours? Yes.
Yeah. So I see that in my school every day.
I see people down in the learning enrichment center who are currently working
through this process at the moment, and they're year 12, year 13.
That's just simply not acceptable, and I think that by making it free, it
encourages whānau to seek that support, and encourages whānau to go get that
assessment so they can get the most help they can.
Because we do know that if children aren't willing to engage and are struggling in
the classroom, they do play up, and it is not fair on our education system that
that happens.
I have done a little bit of teaching myself, so I understand that.
The other question I had for you, and don't worry if you don't know the answer, is
what age is dyslexia best able to be diagnosed?
How early can you diagnose it?
I'm not sure, but I do know, speaking to people who support people with
neurodiversity in our school says that you can pick up on it quite early on.
I don't know the exact age, but it can be picked up quite early.
And if it's not picked up, it can turn into a phonics problem rather than
dyslexia.
Mm. Thank you.
Nate, can I just ask-
Mm-hmm
... when you had your test, do you know how much it cost?
I believe it cost $1,050.
It's expensive, isn't it? Yeah. All right, cool. Thank you.
Yeah, thanks, Nate.
You're lucky to have a great mother.
Yeah.
All right, Nate. And she's lucky to have a great son, I would've said you would've
said to that, Nate.
Yeah, 100%.
All right. Okay, thank you very much, and good luck.
Thank you.
You can put your screen
blurrer back on now. Off. Okay. Thank you.